{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The Committee of Five, or Petka, led this country, and before World War Two, Carpathian Ruthenia was part of this nation, which allied with Yugoslavia and Romania in the Little Entente. Thomas Masaryk helped create this country whose soldiers fought in a Legion along the Trans-Siberian Railway. Edvard Beneš [[BEH-nesh]] led this country when the Sudetenland [[soo-DEH-ten-lahnd]] was annexed after the Munich Agreement. For ten points, name this former Central European country whose western portion was turned into a protectorate by Nazi Germany during World War Two.",
      "answer": "Czechoslovakia or Československo"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, a Loyalist mistook Henry Lee for Banastre [[BAH-nah-ster]] Tarleton in an engagement known as Pyle’s Hacking Match. A horse was shot from under General Charles Cornwallis during a battle in this state which inspired the quote, “Another such victory will ruin the British army.” That pyrrhic victory for the British was fought in this state at Guilford Court House, near modern-day Greensboro. For ten points, name this state whose capital was named for Sir Walter Raleigh.",
      "answer": "North Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "One work by this composer, focusing on the dedication of a theatre in Pest [[PESHT]], laments the Ottoman conquest of Athens. Another work by this composer commemorates the result of the Battle of Vitoria, a defeat for Joseph Bonaparte. This composer of Wellington’s Victory changed the original dedication of a work containing a C- minor funeral march from one specific ruler to a generic “great man.” Napoleon was the original dedicatee of the “Eroica” Symphony by, for ten points, what composer of Für Elise?",
      "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven"
    },
    {
      "question": "A hymn written in favor of the \"Gathering\" of these groups was written by George Loveless, one of the Tolpuddle Martyrs. The Webb siblings wrote a history of these groups, including their \"New Model\" form. Many of these groups signed the Warwick Agreement, allying with the Labour party. In 1871, these groups were legalized under Lord Derby's ministry, but these groups were previously banned under the Combination Acts. Organizing the 1926 General Strike, for ten points, what are these groups which represent laborers?",
      "answer": "Trade Unions in the United Kingdom or Labor Unions 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "This company’s main product may have been inspired by the French beverage Vin Mariani [[mah-ree-AH-nee]]. During Asa Candler's time leading this company, it began bottling operations in Chattanooga. Despite positive taste tests, this company's 1985 \"New\" version of its flagship product was highly criticized. This company, which was founded by John Pemberton, launched its most popular drink during Prohibition in Georgia. For ten points, name this soft drink company, known for its rivalry with Pepsi.",
      "answer": [
        "The Coca-Cola Company",
        "Coke"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2019, this series was remade for French television under the title Mouche [[MOOSH]]. This television show was adapted from a 2013 one-woman play at the Edinburgh Fringe Festival. Enola Holmes director Harry Bradbeer directed every episode of this series other than the pilot, in which the protagonist steals a sculpture of a woman’s torso from her stepmother after being denied a loan for her failing café. The winner of the 2019 Primetime Emmy for Outstanding Comedy Series, for ten points, what is this television show starring Phoebe Waller-Bridge?",
      "answer": "Fleabag"
    },
    {
      "question": "When the Sociedad de Beneficencia [[soh-cee-eh-DAHD deh beh-neh-fee-SEN-see- ah]] did not offer this person its presidency, she started a charitable foundation in her own name. A city built by that foundation was temporarily renamed Ciudad General Belgrano following the \"Liberating Revolution\" that removed this woman’s husband from power. The title “Spiritual Leader of the Nation” was given to, for ten points, what suffragette and supporter of the descamisados, whose life story was depicted in a namesake Andrew Lloyd Webber musical?",
      "answer": [
        "Eva Perón",
        "Evita Perón"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, born in Lower Silesia, began his military career as a cavalry reconnaissance officer. The identity of this man's killer has been debated for decades, with suspects including Cedric Popkin's anti-aircraft gun and flying ace Arthur Roy Brown. This soldier commanded Jasta 11 [[YAH-stuh ELF]] as part of the larger \"Flying Circus\" unit. For ten points, name this colorfully-nicknamed ace German fighter pilot credited with 80 air combat victories in World War One.",
      "answer": [
        "The Red Baron or Manfred Albrecht Freiherr von Richthofen",
        "or Baron von Richthofen 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 4"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2000, John Poulos and James Hoover founded this company in Canada. Sidney Powell claimed to have evidence from a Venezuelan military official proving this company’s products were defective. Mike Lindell of My Pillow was the subject of a defamation lawsuit from this company, whose central products have cumulative and ranked-choice options. Potential tampering with this company's products in Wisconsin and Georgia partly led to a hand recount during the 2020 presidential election. For ten points, name this company which makes electronic voting equipment.",
      "answer": "Dominion Voting Systems Corporation"
    },
    {
      "question": "This president defended Elizabeth Jennings Graham in a court case that helped pave the way for the desegregation of streetcars in his home state. The New York World wrote that during this man's time in office, “no duty was neglected in his administration, and no adventurous project alarmed the nation.\" This president signed into effect the Pendleton Civil Service Reform Act after Charles Guiteau assassinated his predecessor. For ten points, name this 21st president and successor to James Garfield.",
      "answer": "Chester Alan Arthur 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 4"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man stayed in his seat while rioters threw rocks and bottles at him in the Saint- Jean-Baptiste Day parade. The “mania” for this man abated after he married Margaret Sinclair, and to patriate the Constitution, this man's minister, John Turner, created the Victoria Charter. This man enforced the War Measures Act after James Cross and Pierre Laporte were kidnapped by the FLQ. This leader defused the October Crisis and made his nation officially bilingual. For ten points, name this Canadian prime minister, the father of Justin.",
        "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2004, Pierre Trudeau was voted the third greatest Canadian by CBC viewers, behind activist Terry Fox and Tommy Douglas, who was premier of this province from 1944 to 1961. This \"Prairie Province\" is the only one without natural borders.",
        "answer": "Saskatchewan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state's Uinta Mountains contain the Dinosaur National Monument, site of a 1950s activism campaign against the proposed Echo Park Dam. This state is the site of Promontory Summit, where two lines from Sacramento to Omaha were joined to create the first Transcontinental Railroad. The Mountain Meadows Massacre occurred in this state, which was settled by pioneers led by Brigham Young. For ten points, name this state whose population is over fifty percent Mormon.",
        "answer": "Utah"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "From 1935 to 1970, eighteen of the nineteen new land speed records were set on these salt flats to the west of the Great Salt Lake in Utah.",
        "answer": [
          "Bonneville Salt Flats",
          "Bonneville Speedway"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After the Civil War, this general claimed “all, all was lost, except my debts.” Spencer repeating rifles helped one general overrun this man’s defensive fortifications during the Tullahoma Campaign, which followed this man’s defeat at Stones River. This man was replaced by Joseph Johnston after a defeat that included fighting at Missionary Ridge. That defeat occurred after this man avenged himself on William Rosecrans at a battle along a namesake tributary of the Tennessee River. For ten points, name this Confederate general who won the Battle of Chickamauga.",
        "answer": "Braxton Bragg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The loss at the Battle of Stones River crushed Confederate hopes of controlling Middle Tennessee. The West Fork of the Stones River runs through this Middle Tennessee city which gives an alternate name to that battle.",
        "answer": [
          "Murfreesboro",
          "Second Battle of Murfreesboro 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 4"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Journalist Walter Duranty misled Western audiences about this event by describing it as \"an exaggeration or malignant propaganda.\" Robert Conquest discussed this event in The Harvest of Sorrow. While living in Stavropol, Mikhail Gorbachev barely survived this event, in which his father and sisters were killed. This man-made disaster likely occurred in part to weaken the Kulak class who resisted the process of collectivization by Stalin's government. For ten points, name this 1932 to 1933 famine in Soviet Ukraine.",
        "answer": [
          "Holodomor",
          "The Great Famine",
          "Famine in the Ukraine before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The U.S. and most of Western Europe do not recognize the Holodomor as this kind of act, coined by Raphael Lemkin in the 1940s. This act involves intentional action to destroy a people group.",
        "answer": "Genocide"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Take Care clause is found in this article of the U.S. Constitution, which requires a two-thirds majority in the Senate prior to a treaty going into effect. The phase “high crimes and misdemeanors” appears in this article, whose Section One, Clause Seven requires that a certain salary remain at $400,000 for an entire term. The Electoral College was established in this article, whose fourth section deals with impeachment. For ten points, name this article of the U.S. Constitution which outlines the powers of the Executive Branch.",
        "answer": [
          "Article Two",
          "Second Article"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The president also has this power to set aside punishment for an individual's crime. U.S. v. Wilson declared that this power does not legally have to be accepted by the recipient.",
        "answer": "Federal Pardon or Presidential Pardon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Followers of this man were opposed by a rival group known as the Palleschi [[pah- LEH-shee]]. The “Weepers” supported this man who befriended the author of Oration on the Dignity of Man, Pico Della Mirandola. This “man was ruined with his new order of things” according to Machiavelli, who referred to this man as being inadequately armed to enforce his beliefs. Charles VIII’s invasion was welcomed by this man, who ordered the burning of sinful objects in the Bonfire of the Vanities. For ten points, name this Dominican friar who preached extensively in Florence.",
        "answer": "Girolamo Savonarola"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Savonarola openly flouted the orders of this Pope, refusing to join his Holy League. This Pope, whose son Cesare [[CHEH-sah-reh]] was an inspiration for Machiavelli's The Prince, was a member of the Borgia [[BOR-zhah]] family.",
        "answer": "Pope Alexander VI"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The maenianum secundum was a section of this structure in which ordinary citizens could watch events. For the opening of this structure, one emperor gave two events called naumachia [[now-MAY-kee-ah]], which lasted until its hypogeum [[hai-puh-JEE-um]] was built to support other activities. This landmark's construction was started by Emperor Vespasian and completed by his son, Titus. Also known as the Flavian Amphitheatre, for ten points, what is this structure in central Rome which hosted gladiator fights?",
        "answer": [
          "Colosseum",
          "Flavian Amphitheatre before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Colosseum had several of these exits, which were large enough for crowds to fit through. Derived from the Latin for \"to spew forth,\" these were not places where Romans practiced a binge and purge cycle, despite popular myth.",
        "answer": "Vomitoriums or Vomitoria"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was the namesake of a pottery club founded by Edith Guerrier and Edith Brown of the Saturday Evening Girls Club to help provide young women with income. This man commanded an artillery detachment during an expedition to capture a region of Maine after it had been taken over by the British. That disastrous 1779 Penobscot Expedition occurred several years after this man undertook a midnight ride to warn minutemen of the approaching British. For ten points, name this Bostonian silversmith.",
        "answer": "Paul Revere"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Paul Revere's midnight ride was immortalized in a poem by this American author of Evangeline and The Song of Hiawatha.",
        "answer": "Henry Wadsworth Longfellow"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Obama-Era Controversies",
      "prompt": "Concerning people, places, or things related to Obama-era controversies, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Act which resulted in the creation of HealthCare.gov.",
          "answer": [
            "Affordable Care Act",
            "ACA",
            "Obamacare"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Libyan city where Ambassador Chris Stevens was killed in 2012 during an attack on U.S. facilities.",
          "answer": "Benghazi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose president, Bashar al-Assad, crossed Obama's \"red line\" by using chemical weapons.",
          "answer": "Syrian Arab Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Consultant who leaked information about NSA global surveillance programs.",
          "answer": "Edward Snowden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Detention camp, which Obama described as a \"sad chapter in American history\" but failed to fully close.",
          "answer": [
            "Guantánamo Bay detention camp",
            "Gitmo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Products manufactured by Solyndra which obtained $535 million in loans by misleading federal officials.",
          "answer": "Solar panels"
        },
        {
          "question": "Professor whom Obama invited to the White House following his arrest at his home in Cambridge, Massachusetts.",
          "answer": "Henry Louis Gates, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Outfit worn by Obama which drew disapproval from those who claimed it was too casual for a press conference.",
          "answer": [
            "Tan suit",
            "Tan jacket 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 4"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "European Minority Languages and People",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Tristan, of Tristan and Isolde, would have spoken Cornish, a member of this language family.",
          "answer": [
            "Celtic",
            "Gaelic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighbor of Finland where Karelian is spoken which fought the Great Northern War.",
          "answer": [
            "Russian Federation",
            "Tsardom of Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern island language spoken with a Punic and Nuragic component which is considered closest to Latin.",
          "answer": "Sardinian"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northwestern Spanish people whose language is closer to Portuguese and contains Celtic roots.",
          "answer": "Galicians"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only language isolate in Europe, spoken by a people coming from a region on the Bay of Biscay.",
          "answer": "Basque or Euskara"
        },
        {
          "question": "Reindeer herding peoples of Northern Europe who helped destroy a secret German nuclear facility during World War Two.",
          "answer": [
            "Sámi",
            "Lapps",
            "Laplanders"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Slavic people whose territory was ceded to Prussia in the War of the Austrian Succession.",
          "answer": "Silesians"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mongolic language, the only one spoken in Europe, used in a Federal Subject of Russia in the Caucasus.",
          "answer": "Kalmyk Oirat 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 4"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Late Antique Arabia and the Formation of Islam",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Belief to which Islam adheres that there is only one God.",
          "answer": [
            "Monotheism",
            "Monotheistic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Trading city where Muhammad was born around 570 CE.",
          "answer": "Mecca"
        },
        {
          "question": "New name given to the city of Yathrib by Muhammad, which means \"the city\" in Arabic.",
          "answer": "Medina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central shrine of Islam's holiest city, constructed in the shape of a cube.",
          "answer": "The Kaaba"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruling tribe of Islam's holiest city, of which Muhammad was a member.",
          "answer": [
            "Quraysh",
            "Banu Hashim"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Arabic term given to the journey of Muhammad and his followers after his assassination was ordered.",
          "answer": "Hijra or Hegira"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region in which Islam's holiest cities are located, today in western Saudi Arabia.",
          "answer": [
            "Hijaz",
            "Western Province"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ethiopian general who campaigned in Arabia in the 6th century and attempted an attack on the holy city in the Year of the Elephant.",
          "answer": "Abraha al-Ashram or Abreha 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 4"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was prompted by attempts at tax collection by John Bampton. John of Gaunt's Savoy Palace was destroyed during this event, which was ended after Henry Despenser won the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "North Walsham. Future king Henry IV was almost executed after being captured during this event. A meeting at Smithfield during this event resulted in William (10 pts)",
        "Walworth knifing one man to death. For ten points, what rebellion, led by Jack Straw and Wat Tyler, nearly ended the reign of Richard II of England?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Peasants’ Revolt",
        "Wat Tyler’s Revolt before mentioned",
        "Great Rising",
        "\"Rebellion\"",
        "\"Uprising\" in place of \"Revolt\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In what is now this state, the Second Battle of Vinegar Hill was fought during the Castle Hill Rebellion. Mid-nineteenth century modernization efforts in this state were overseen by Lachlan (20 pts)",
        "Macquarie [[LAH-kluhn muh-KWAH-ree]]. Land in this state belonging to the “O’Brien Estate” was turned into (10 pts)",
        "Bondi Beach. A series of gold rushes in the mid-nineteenth century set the stage for a rivalry between this state’s major city and Melbourne. For ten points, what Australian state's capital was named for Thomas Townshend, First Viscount Sydney?"
      ],
      "answer": "New South Wales"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At a 1920 convention held in this state, Carrie Chapman Catt founded the League of Women Voters. One 1906 novel set in this state attempted to expose the harsh living conditions for its largest city's (20 pts)",
        "immigrant population. In this state in 2017, a bill prohibiting police from arresting someone based on immigration status was signed by Governor (10 pts)",
        "Bruce Rauner. For ten points, name this state, the setting of the novel which prompted the Meat Inspection Act, The Jungle."
      ],
      "answer": "Illinois"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "One work from this artist depicts a large ponderosa pine tree on D. H. Lawrence's ranch, and this artist produced a series of cloudscapes while living at Abiquiú [[AB-ih-kyoo]]. This person caused a sensation as the subject of a 1921 exhibition of mostly (*) nude photographs by photographer Alfred Stieglitz, whom she later married. Jimson Weed and (*) Cow's Skull: Red, White, and Blue are among the best known works of, for ten points, what \"Mother of American modernism,\" known for her paintings of New Mexico landscapes, animal bones, and flowers?"
      ],
      "answer": "Georgia O'Keeffe 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 4"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Brownrigg was sent a sample of this resource by Charles Wood that was the subject of numerous experiments. Charles III gave the entire government supply of this resource to Pierre-François Chabaneau [[shah-bah-NOH]] for research, resulting in the creation of its malleable form. (20 pts)",
        "Antonio de Ulloa [[oo-YOH-ah]] is said to have been the first European to discover this metal, which was often discarded due to the belief that it made (10 pts)",
        "gold impure. Derived from a term meaning “little silver,” for ten points, what precious metal has atomic number 78 and chemical symbol Pt [[PEE- TEE]]?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Platinum",
        "Pt before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. These two countries engaged in the diplomatic Madrid Principles and Prague Process. These two countries fought a war that included Operation Ring and the Khojaly [[HO-jah-luh]] Massacre. Operation (20 pts)",
        "Goranboy was launched by one of these two countries in a conflict that ended with the Bishkek Protocol. These two nations fought for the Lachin [[LAH-cheen]] Corridor in a 1988 to 1994 war in (10 pts)",
        "Nagorno-Karabakh [[kah-ruh-BAHK]]. For ten points, name these two nations in the Caucasus, governed from Yerevan and Baku."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Armenia and Republic of Azerbaijan",
        "Hayastani Hanrapetut'yun for Armenia",
        "Azerbaycan Respublikasi for Azerbaijan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This period was preceded by one nicknamed \"closing curtain,\" during which the slogan \"Sonnō jōi\" [[SOH-NOH JO-EE]] was used. This era, which followed the Bakumatsu period, accelerated (20 pts)",
        "industrialization in its country under the national slogan \"Enrich the country, strengthen the military.\" Dissatisfaction with reforms during this period led to the Satsuma Rebellion, in which disaffected (10 pts)",
        "samurai revolted. This period included the passage of the proto-constitutional Charter Oath. For ten points, name this era of modernization which began after the fall of the Tokugawa Shogunate."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Meiji Restoration",
        "Meiji Period",
        "Meiji Renewal"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A crossing at this battle was planned at Skinkers Neck, and artillery was placed at Stafford Heights. Confusion at this battle arose from using the less forceful phrase \"to seize\" rather than \"to (20 pts)",
        "carry.\" The Right Grand Division at this battle was led by Edwin Vose Sumner. A plan to cross the Rappahannock River to reach Richmond at this battle failed and forced a confrontation at (10 pts)",
        "Marye's Heights after pontoon bridges were assembled. For ten points, name this 1862 battle in Virginia, a victory for Robert E. Lee."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Fredericksburg 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 4"
    }
  ]
}